Guide to the James Gates Percival Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Gates Percival collection
1800-1944
1820-1850
YCAL MSS 703
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.34
(16 boxes) + 1 broadside folder, 1 art
The James Gates Percival Collection consist of writings, notebooks, personal papers, correspondence, maps, and other papers that document Percival's life and work. Writings are autograph manuscripts of poetry and prose compositions on linguistics, geology, and geography, including several drafts of his Report on the Geology of Connecticut, as well as chemistry notes by West Point professor James Cutbush. Percival's notebooks contain writings and notes on a broad range of topics in addition to his classroom notes from school, college, and medical school days. Personal papers include contracts, agreements, and subscriber lists related to his publications; inventories and invoices documenting his large library collection; and other financial papers, primarily bills for personal expenses including room, board, and clothing. Correspondence files hold letters to and from many prominent colleagues and scholars such as Benjamin Silliman and Edward C. Herrick in New Haven, friends including George Hayward in Boston, his publishers Sidney Babcock, Samuel G. Goodrich, and Samuel Walker, and editors such as Eliza Leslie and Louisa C. Tuthill. Percival was a member of the New Haven Sing-Song Club and the collection documents his contributions to that organization. Also present is a portrait painting of Percival by his brother Edwin Percival, and a group of papers regarding Percival's life and work complied by J. H. Ward, Herbert E. Gregory, and others, including a memoir of him by Caroline Howard Gilman.
Percival, James Gates, 1795-1856
Cutbush, James, 1788-1823
Gilman, Caroline Howard, 1794-1888
Gregory, Herbert E. (Herbert Ernest), 1869-1952
Percival, Edwin, 1793-1847?
Ward, J. H. (Julius Hammond), 1837-1897
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Julius H. Ward (Yale 1860), after 1866. Other acquisitions are noted at the folder level.
Custodial History
Althea Green Wilson discusses the history of Percival's papers in the Yale University Library Gazette 28 (no. 2, October 1953). Several of the items in the collection were published in J. H. Ward's volume The Life and Letters of James Gates Percival (Boston: Ticknor and Fields, 1866).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James Gates Percival (1795-1856)
James Gates Percival, an American poet, physician, linguist, geologist, bibliophile, and autodidact, was born in Kensington, Connecticut, on September 15, 1795. After attending boarding school he entered Yale College in 1810 and graduated in 1815. Percival began medical school at the University of Pennsylvania in 1818 but returned to Yale to complete his degree in 1820. He practiced medicine in Connecticut and Charleston, South Carolina, and briefly taught chemistry at West Point in 1824. Returning to Connecticut, he studied linguistics and European languages (particularly German), assisted Noah Webster with his American Dictionary of the English Language (1828), and prepared new editions of Vicesimus Knox's Elegant Extracts (1826) and Conrad Malte-Brun's A System of Universal Geography (1834). His former Yale professor and mentor Benjamin Silliman encouraged Percival's appointment as Connecticut state geologist in 1835, which led to his amassing great quantities of geological data that were eventually published in his volume Report on the Geology of the State of Connecticut (1842). Hired to survey lead mines in Illinois and Wisconsin in 1853, Percival spent his last years in the Midwest, becoming the state geologist of Wisconsin in 1854; he died in Hazel Green, Wisconsin, on May 2, 1856.
Percival began writing poetry while in boarding school, his most notable work being the epic-length poem "The Commerciad"; later verses were published in the early 1820s in the New Haven Microscope, the United States Literary Gazette, and other newspapers. His collected Poems (1821) included his well-regarded "Prometheus" and inspired the publication of Prometheus Part II with Other Poems (1822). His series Clio I, Clio II (both 1822), and Clio III (1827) were followed fifteen years later by his final volume of poetry, The Dream of a Day (1843).
Scope and Contents
The James Gates Percival Papers consist of writings, notebooks, personal papers, correspondence, maps, and other papers. Writings are autograph manuscripts of poetry and prose compositions on linguistics, geology, and geography, including several drafts of his Report on the Geology of Connecticut, as well as chemistry notes by West Point professor James Cutbush. Percival's notebooks contain writings and notes on a broad range of topics in addition to classroom notes from school, college, and his medical school days. Personal papers include contracts, agreements, and subscriber lists related to his publications, inventories and invoices documenting his large library collection, and other financial papers, primarily bills for personal expenses including room, board, and clothing. Correspondence files hold letters to and from many prominent colleagues and scholars such as Benjamin Silliman and Edward C. Herrick in New Haven, friends including George Hayward in Boston, his publishers Sidney Babcock, Samuel G. Goodrich, and Samuel Walker, and editors such as Eliza Leslie and Louisa C. Tuthill. Percival was a member of the New Haven Sing-Song Club and the collection documents his contributions to that organization. Also present is a portrait painting of Percival by his brother Edwin Percival, and small groups of papers regarding Percival's life and work complied by J. H. Ward, Herbert E. Gregory, and others, including a memoir of him by Caroline Howard Gilman.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Writings, 1800-1854. II. Notebooks and Notes, 1807-1840. III. Personal Papers, 1819-1851. IV. Correspondence, 1816-1856. V. Printed Material, 1822-1856. VI. Maps and Artwork, 1830-1840. VII. Other Papers Related to Percival and His Work, 1859-1944.
Book collecting -- United States; Collectors and collecting -- United States; Geography -- United States; Geologists -- United States; Geology -- United States; Linguists -- United States; Linguistics -- United States; Linguists' writings; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Geological maps -- United States -- 19th century; Manuscript maps -- United States -- 19th century; Oil paintings (visual works) -- United States -- 19th century; Subscription lists (Publishing) -- Connecticut -- New Haven -- 19th century; Geologists -- United States -- 19th century; Linguists -- United States -- 19th century; Poets -- United States -- 19th century; Babcock, Sidney, 1797?-1884; Cutbush, James, 1788-1823; Gilman, Caroline Howard, 1794-1888; Goodrich, Samuel G. (Samuel Griswold), 1793-1860; Gregory, Herbert E. (Herbert Ernest), 1869-1952; Hayward, George, 1791-1863; Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1811-1862; Leslie, Eliza, 1787-1858; Percival, Edwin, 1793-1847?; Percival, James Gates, 1795-1856; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Tuthill, Louisa C. (Louisa Caroline), 1798-1879; Walker, Samuel, active 1832-1851; Ward, J. H. (Julius Hammond), 1837-1897; Yvonnet, James Lawrence, -1824; New Haven Sing-Song Club
- Writings, 1800-1854; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into five subseries: Poetry, Linguistics, Prose, Geology, Geography, and Other Topics; within those subseries material is arranged by the consecutive numbers assigned by library staff.
  Scope and Contents
  The series primarily contains autograph manuscripts by Percival that include his literary and scientific work. The folders hold drafts and notes as well as finished compositions meant for publication.
  - Poetry
    - 1. Clio I: Essay on the Imaginative Mind and original manuscript of long poem beginning "The world is full of poetry...", undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Begins: Ego, apis matinae more, modoque. Autograph manuscript, incomplete.
    - 2. Clio I: financial details, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Manuscript in unidentified hand.
    - 3. Clio II: Preface, and fragment of poem entitled "Freedom", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Two versions of preface, both incomplete.
    - 4. Clio III: errata with title: "Errors of Clio" and autograph manuscript drafts, many incomplete, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Removed from his Clio III (New York, 1827); gift of Owen Franklin Aldis (Yale 1874), 1911.
    - 5. The Commerciad, A Mock Heroic, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Autograph manuscript of preface and first canto. 85[5] pages. Page 74-[89] miscellaneous poems and verses unpublished. Last leaf has list of militia personnel by towns with distance from Boston.
    - 6. The Dream of a Day and Other Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      Autograph manuscripts of poems collected and published in 1843. Includes folder of poems translated from German and Russian.
    - 7. Prometheus, Parts I and II, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      Autograph manuscript incomplete.
    - 8. Prometheus, Part II. Preface and Lesser Poems., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Autograph manuscript incomplete, and original manuscript drafts of poems published in 1822.
    - 9. The Wreck, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Original manuscript, incomplete.
    - 10. Zamor, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Manuscript fragment of a tragedy.
    - 11. Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
      Original manuscript drafts and fragments of poems published. Identified in the two volumes published in Boston, 1859.
    - 12. Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
      Original manuscript drafts and fragments of published and unpublished poems, unidentified.
    - 13. Youthful verse, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Manuscripts of poems written at the ages of 16, 18, and when he was in college.
    - 14. Aeschylus' Prometheus Boundleaves, 1823, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Autograph manuscript of Percival's translation. Accompanied by fragment of a letter to "Dear Sir", New Haven, May 28, 1823. On verso of leaf 2 of his translation of Aeschylus' Prometheus Bound [q.v.]; and a letter to his mother, New Haven, June 16, 1823, on version of leaves 3-4 of his translation of Aeschylus' Prometheus Bound.
    - 15-16. Phi Beta Kappa poem, Yale College, with a fair copy in Percival's hand, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 17. Athelstan, A Tragedy, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Autograph manuscript, incomplete.
    - 18. Lord Byron's Farewell, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Manuscript of poem of eleven stanzas. Accompanied by: "A Name, Byron," unfinished manuscript copy. On same page: poem of three stanzas beginning: Soft to slumber on ye moss bring...; "Dream of L. Byron," manuscript verses; and farewell of Child Harold from Lord Byron. Manuscript copy of verses.
    - 19. God, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Autograph manuscript verses, begins: "O! Thou, infinite in extent."
    - 20. Hail to the Morning..., undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Poem of three stanzas, autograph manuscript.
      Removed from his The Dream of a Day (New Haven, 1843); gift of Owen Franklin Aldis (Yale 1874), 1911.
    - 21. Homer; original manuscript draft of a translation of a poem by Stolberg, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 22. Horatian Odes, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Autograph manuscript of Percival's translations of Odes of Horace. L.IV.3 joined with sealing wax.
    - 23. January Thaw, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Manuscript poem of four stanzas.
    - 24. Linnean Ode, 1826 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Original manuscript draft, incomplete. Printed in Clio III with title: Birth-day of Linnaeus.
    - 25. The Seasons, a Serial., undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Original manuscript of part of the sonnet series "Slavonia."
      Purchased on the Plain Fund, 1938.
    - 26. The Spirit of Life, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Autograph poem.
    - 27. To A Belle, 1828 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Autograph manuscript signed and dated. Published in Knickerbocker, December 1837. Copy not in Percival's hand.
    - 28. To Live Beyond the Grave..., undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Autograph manuscript of poem with signature pasted on.
    - 29. To Those..., undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Autograph manuscript signed of one verse of poetry, with two manuscript copies in Percival's hand.
    - 30. Unity, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Four-verse song with musical notes along the top of the page. On verso: Miss Charlotte Seldon.
    - 31. Written After Reading The Paradise of Coquettes, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Manuscript of long poem [unpublished?]
    - 32. The Whig Amnesty, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Manuscript copy of his poem of five stanzas, and a card with Italian quotation and his signature inserted.
      Purchased on the Henry P. Driggs Memorial Fund.
    - 33. Political campaign songs, 1840 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Autograph manuscripts of words written by Percival, including The Whig Town and Specimens of a New Nursery.
    - 34. Notes on poets and poetry, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Miscellaneous manuscript fragments including lists of poets.
    - 35. Recollections. Poem. George Pallavicini Speaks in Prison., undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - 36. Song written as an accompaniment to an original Air by the Blind Harper, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - 37. Goodrich, Maryanne Wolcott, poem., circa 1815 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - 38. [Dedication], 1822 Nov (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Begins: "To those,/Who have wakened the fancy," His title: "To those, Who have wakened the fancy" (not found in editions of Percival's verse).
      Purchased from the Seven Gables Bookshop on the George B. Alvord Fund, 1957.
    - 39. Classic Melodies., undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Autograph manuscript (incomplete?). Verse imitations of ancient measures, with an introductory note in prose. Contents: Elegiac - iambic - Anacreontic - Anapestic, I.
      Gift of James T. Babb (Yale 1924), 1962.
    - 40. "The Irish Harper", undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Purchased from Walter R. Benjamin Autographs on the George B. Alvord Fund, 1964.
    - 41. "Half nonsense verses, composed to sing the Marseillaise, without forcing the words", undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
      Purchased from the Seven Gables Bookshop on the Danford N. Barney, Jr. Fund, 1965.
    - 42. "Bear this present to my maiden...", undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
      Removed from: his Poems, vol. I (London: 1824), 2008; gift of Francis B. Trowbridge (Yale 1887, LLB 1890), 1899.
    - 43."O'! Sing to me!", undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
      General note
      Addressed to Maria Worcester
      Purchased from Claudia Queen on the George B. Alvord Fund, 2009.
  - Linguistics
    - 100. Studies in Verse, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Manuscript verses in imitation of verses in different languages namely: Sanscrit (sic), Persian, Arabic, and Eastern species, with scansion notes.
    - 101. Epigrammes Carlistes, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Six epigrams in French. On reverse: Epigrammi Pontificali in Italian and Bundes Epigrammen in German. Autograph manuscript. And another copy of the Italian and two of the French epigrams with other notes on the same sheet.
    - 102. On the relations of languages, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Manuscript essay and table exhibiting the conditions and affinities of the principal known languages.
    - 103. Linguistic notes: comparative, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
      Miscellaneous manuscript notes chiefly on general Indo-European languages.
    - 104. Linguistic notes: Indo-European, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
      Manuscript notes on a comparative Indo-European grammar never published.
    - 105. Translations of poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
      From various foreign languages, published and unpublished, but chiefly fragmentary and unidentified.
    - 106. Linguistic notes: English, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Manuscript notes concerning English grammar.
    - 107. Linguistic notes: French, Spanish, Basque, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
      Manuscript notes on grammar as well as translations from Basque.
    - 108. Linguistic notes: Gaelic, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
      Manuscript notes on Gaelic (Irish) words and grammar. With his manuscript notes on Shaw's Gaelic grammar.
    - 109. Linguistic notes: German, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Manuscript notes on German words and grammar.
    - 110. German poems, original and translated, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
      Autograph manuscripts.
      Partial contents: - Die Wurde den Frauen. - Der Tanz. - Zu meinem Herrn. - Der Levenstreit. - Der deutsche Verein. - The German maiden's patriot song. - The doves. - The shop-girl. - Der deutsche Patriot.
    - 111. Linguistic notes: Greek and Latin, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Manuscript notes on Greek and Latin words and Grammar. Including Greek poems with translation.
    - 112. Linguistic notes: Hebrew, Arabic, Syrian, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
      Manuscript notes on Hebrew words and grammar; an alphabetical table comparing Arabic, Syrian, Samar, and Hebrew letters; and a calendar in Yiddish (not in Percival's hand).
    - 113. Linguistic notes; Hungarian, Bohemian, Czech, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
      Manuscript notes on the Hungarian language and on Bohemian literature, a poem translated from Bohemian, and Czech poetry.
    - 114. Linguistic notes: Italian, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
      Manuscript notes on Italian grammar.
    - 115. Linguistic notes: Russian, Polish, Armenian, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
      Manuscript notes on the Russian and Polish languages with examples of poetry from both.
    - 116. Linguistic notes: Sanscrit, Bengalese, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Manuscript notes on the Sanscrit and Bengalese languages.
    - 117. Linguistic notes: Scandinavian, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
      Manuscript notes on the Danish, Swedish, and Eskimo languages with examples of poetry with translations from Danish and Swedish. And "To Ole Bull." Manuscript of poem in Norwegian with English translation on reverse.
  - Prose
    - 200. On the Art of Printing and the Freedom of the Press, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
      Autograph manuscript of an oration or college disputation.
    - 201. The Atheneum, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
      Prospectus in Percival's hand announcing his editorship of the magazine. It did not materialize.
    - 202. On Greek liberty, undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
      Autograph manuscript of essay. 3 pages with verses on page 4.
    - 203. Kidd's Money, undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
      Autograph manuscript of essay on Captain Kidd.
    - 204. Letters on the Author of Junius, by E. H. Barker., undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Quotation from the appendix which refers to Percival.
    - 205. The Next President, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      Original autograph manuscript of editorial for the Daily Herald, on the presidential election stating that he will not support Calhoun. Never printed.
    - 206. Newspaper contributions, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
      Original autograph manuscripts of articles chiefly for the Daily Herald and in the form of letters to the editors. Subjects are chiefly linguistic.
    - 207. Nosology, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      Autograph manuscript fragment of article on the nose printed in the Daily Herald August 17, 1833.
    - 208. On Bowring's translations, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
      Autograph manuscript article (incomplete) with reference to Talvj.
    - 209. Oration on the Comparative Value of a Scientific and Military Reputation, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      Autograph manuscript of Yale College commencement oration.
    - 210. Phi Beta Kappa oration, Yale College, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      Manuscript copy in Percival's hand.
    - 211. The Plague of Athens from YE 2d Book of Thucydides Peloponessian War, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
      English translation by Percival.
    - 212. Prospectus for a Literary Paper and Prospectus of a New Weekly Miscellany, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
      George B. Alvord (Yale 1895) Collection.
    - 213. A story untitled and unfinished beginning: In the winter of seventy-six..., undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - 214. The Travellers' Club No. II, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
      On reverse: Poem beginning: When first from the land of the tyrants & slaves...
    - 215. Prose, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
      Miscellaneous autograph manuscripts, fragmentary, of his prose writing, probably translations.
    - 216. Anti-phrenology, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
      Autograph manuscript fragment of article against phrenology.
    - 217. Port Folio No. II, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
      Autograph manuscript of article on writing as a trade.
    - 218. Address written in resignation as president of some medical association, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - 219. National university, undated (Box 3, Folder 84)
      Moved from letters 676 in 1964.
  - Geology
    - 300. Report on the Geology of the State of Connecticut, circa 1840 (Box 3, Folder 85)
      Five incomplete drafts of the report with extraneous matter, one on the lead and silver mines of Middletown.
      Gift of Chester R. Longwell (Yale PhD 1920), 1939.
    - 301. Report on the Geology of the State of Connecticut, circa 1840 (Box 3, Folder 86)
      Complete draft of report rewritten before published.
    - 303. Report on the Geology of the State of Connecticut, circa 1840 (Box 3, Folder 87-89)
      Autograph manuscript of report as it was finally published. preface incomplete, with index at end.
    - 304. Geological maps and formation notes for his Report on the Geology of the State of Connecticut, 1835-1840 (Box 3, Folder 90)
      Recatalogued from Z117.011, v.1, in 1941.
    - 305. Synopsis of the Geological Map of the State [Connecticut], 1835-1840 (Box 3, Folder 91)
      Outline of geological structure of Connecticut as reported in his report on the state.
    - 306. Statement of accounts of his tours through Connecticut in making the geological survey of the state, 1835-1840 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - 307. First report on the geology of Wisconsin, circa 1854 (Box 3, Folder 93)
      Incomplete manuscript.
    - 308. Report on the Trap and sandstone of New Jersey, undated (Box 3, Folder 94)
      Autograph manuscript fragments of the report. See Series V for a related map.
    - 309. Lake Erie trip, a geological account, undated (Box 3, Folder 95)
      Incomplete.
    - 310. General View of the Geology of the South & Middle Bass Islands and their Appendages..., undated (Box 3, Folder 96)
      Autograph manuscript complete.
    - 311. Coal Mine in Nova Scotia, undated (Box 3, Folder 97)
      Autograph manuscript of geological report.
      Transferred from Rare Book Room, 1952.
    - 312. Views on a Railroad Route from New Haven by Danbury to Fishkill, circa 1849 (Box 3, Folder 98)
      Autograph manuscript report addressed to a committee.
    - 313. Geology notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 99)
      Miscellaneous and fragmentary notes on geology of Connecticut, Wisconsin, and possibly New Jersey.
    - 314. Testimony of geological formation in Glastonbury, 1850 Jan 31 (Box 3, Folder 100)
      Includes record of Percival's expenses on six journeys from New Haven to Glastonbury
  - Geography
    - 350. Malte-Brun, A System of Universal Geography, circa 1834 (Box 4, Folder 101)
      Autograph manuscript notes and maps used in his revision, with two other maps.
    - 351. Malte-Brun, A System of Universal Geography, circa 1834 (Box 4, Folder 102)
      Autograph manuscript notes, corrections, and additions with 1 leaf of corrected proof on "Europe."
    - 352. "The Varieties of the Human Race", circa 1825 (Box 4, Folder 103)